Finding Aid for Edward H. McNamara papers, 1928-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward H. McNamara papers 1928-2007, 1987-2006
McNamara, Edward H.
(in 3 boxes)
2 linear feet
0790 Aa 2
Papers of Edward H. McNamara (1926-2006), Democratic southeastern Michigan politician, served as Wayne county executive (1987-2002), Mayor of Livonia (1970-1986), and Livonia city councilman (1962-1968). The collection includes newspaper clippings, biographical materials, miscellaneous from his political career, and visual materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Mrs. Lucille McNamara (donor no. 9882 ) in 2007.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Edward Howard McNamara was born in Detroit, Michigan on September 21, 1926. He served in the United States Navy during World War II, from July 1944 to June 1946. Under the G.I. Bill, McNamara attended the University of Detroit, and graduated with a bachelor's degree in philosophy and political science in 1959. He also completed one and a half years at the University of Detroit law school.
From 1948 to 1970, he was employed at the Michigan Bell Telephone Company. While employed there, McNamara was elected to a two-year term as Livonia city councilman in 1962, and re-elected to four-year terms in 1964 and 1968. He became the council president in 1968, and was elected Mayor of Livonia in 1970. He served as mayor until 1986. He was then elected as Wayne County Executive, and served in that position from 1987 to 2002.
As county executive, McNamara's lasting contribution was in improving the Detroit Metropolitan Airport. His efforts led to a $1.6 billion renovation of the airport, which included the addition of two runways, a new access road, an 11,000 car parking structure and a 97-gate terminal for Northwest Airlines. The terminal was dedicated to McNamara for his efforts, and was formally named the Edward H. McNamara Terminal.
He was also known for eliminating Wayne county's significant debt, renewing social services to the elderly population in the county, and negotiating deals for new baseball and football stadiums in downtown Detroit.
McNamara's political career was brought under suspicion in November of 2002, when Federal Bureau of Investigation agents and state police raided his office, seeking evidence for a federal grand jury investigation dealing with corruption in airport contracts and campaign fund-raising by his administration. No hearings were ever called, and all charges against McNamara and his staff were dropped in early 2007.
In late 2002, shortly after leaving office, McNamara was diagnosed with a rare form of cancer of the lymphatic system. He died of heart failure on February 19, 2006.
The Edward H. McNamara papers largely concern his public political career. These papers do not include the records of his various office and administrations. Instead, they largely present a favorable picture of the political life of McNamara, and highlight his achievements.
Subjects:
McNamara, Edward H.; Detroit Metro Airport.; Livonia (Mich.); Wayne County (Mich.). Executive.; Wayne County (Mich.)--Politics and government.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
McNamara, Edward H.; Archer, Dennis.; Clinton, Bill, 1946-; Gephardt, Richard A. (Richard Andrew), 1941-; Patterson, L. Brooks.
Genre Terms:
DVDs.; Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Newspaper Clippings
  The Newspaper Clippings series covers McNamara's political career from 1962 until the end of investigations against him and his staff in 2007. This includes various events in his political life, including his election in 1970 as City of Livonia mayor and Wayne County Executive in 1987, measures he tried to implement in the various offices he held, the end of his political career in 2002 and his death in 2006.
  - 1962-1989 (Box 1)
  - 1990-1996 (Box 1)
  - 1998-2002 (Box 1)
  - 2006-2007 (Box 1)
- Biographical Materials
  The Biographical Materials series includes a copy of the manuscript of McNamara's biography, and biographical notes written during various periods of his political career. This series also includes memories collected by his family, friends and political acquaintances, compiled after McNamara's death. The folder on the Dedication of the Edward H. McNamara Terminal includes letters written to the Wayne County Board of Commissioners supporting the motion to name the new airport terminal after McNamara by various state legislators and other important people in Michigan, including Senators Carl Levin and Debbie Stabenow, Governor John Engler, and Detroit Regional Chamber President Richard E. Blouse, Jr.
  - Biography manuscript (Box 2)
  - Biographical Notes and Collected Memories (Box 2)
  - Honors and Awards Received 1979-2006 (Box 2)
  - Dedication of the Edward H. McNamara Terminal 1996-2001 (Box 2)
- Political Career
  The Political Career series includes speeches and campaign materials of McNamara, as well as polls and reports taken of his constituents as Wayne County Executive. This series does not include any correspondence.
  - Campaign Materials (Box 2)
  - Citizen's Survey 1985 (Box 2)
  - Detroit Survey, Reaction to Archer Decision on Casinos 1998 (Box 2)
  - Wayne County Reports 2000-2002 (Box 2)
  - State of the County Address 1990-1993 (Box 2)
  - Speeches 1985-2002, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series includes three folders of photographs, 21 videocassettes (VHS), 3 DVDs and 1 CD. The photographs are of various subjects, including his family, friends and political acquaintances. Of special note are photographs of McNamara with Detroit Mayor Dennis Archer and Oakland County Executive L. Brooks Patterson, with President Bill Clinton, and with Presidential candidate Richard Gephardt. The videocassettes, DVDs and CD recordings include McNamara's campaign TV and radio spots, scattered episodes of the Brooks and Ed Show (with L. Brooks Patterson and Ed McNamara), the annual Leadership Policy Conference held on Mackinac Island, several State of Wayne County addresses, various interviews throughout his political career, the ground breaking and dedication ceremonies of the Edward H. McNamara Terminal at Detroit Metro Airport, and miscellaneous news broadcasts. The videotapes available in Box 3 are VHS unless otherwise specified.
  - Photographs
    - McNamara with Various Groups (Includes portraits and McNamara family) (Box 2)
    - McNamara at Detroit Metro Airport 1998-2002 (CD with Descriptions) (Box 2)
    - McNamara with Political Acquaintances (William Clinton, Richard Gephardt, Dennis Archer and L. Brooks Patterson) (Box 2)
  - Videotapes
    VHS unless otherwise indicated
    - Brooks and Ed Show (L. Brooks Patterson and Edward McNamara)
      - First Episode, "Future of the Region at End of Coleman Young's Mayoral Stint", with guest Jon Pepper, Detroit News columnist (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 1)
      - "Malice Green Trial Outcome", with guest Kym Worthy, Assistant Prosecutor (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 2)
      - "Campaign Fundraising", with guest Geoffrey Fieger, attorney to Jack Kevorkian (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 3)
      - With guest Governor John Engler 1993 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 4)
    - Annual Leadership Policy Conference
      - 1992 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 5)
      - 2000 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 6)
      - 2001 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 7)
      - 2003 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 8)
    - State of the County Address
      - 1989 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 9)
      - 1990 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 10)
      - 1991 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 11)
    - Interviews
      - "Perceptions" 1985 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 12)
      - "Issues Livonia" 1988 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 13)
      - "Up Front" (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 14)
    - Spots
      - "Family" 1994 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 15)
      - "Tolerance" 2001 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 16)
      - "Airport Security" 2001 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 17)
      - "Metro Airport-Now Open" 2002, (CD (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 18)
    - Miscellaneous
      - "Farewell, Mayor McNamara" 1986 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 19)
      - "Presidential Ground Breaking, Metro Airport" 1996 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 20)
      - "Spotlight-Newsmakers of the Year" 1996, (DVD (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 21)
      - "Press Conference, 'He Will Not Run'" 2001, (DVD (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 22)
      - "Spotlight-Edward H. McNamara, 1926-2006" 2006 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 23)
      - "Michigan Legislator's Tributes to Edward McNamara 2006 (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 24)
      - "Ed McNamara Terminal Dedication" 2006, (DVD (Box 3)
        (Tape no. 25)